foreign
specific questions or any
surprise questions
so we thought to bring up the this
Suitor called the relay chariots
and it's where vulnerable saripota he
hears of a a monk praised by other monks
and so he decides to go and visit visit
him and his name is uh Venable punya
so he he eventually finds and then asks
him a few questions
he says my friend is the holy life lived
under the blessed one
and punya replies yes
is the whole life lived under the
blessed one for the sake of Purity in
terms of virtue
just no
then is the holy life lit for the sake
of Purity in terms of mind no
in terms of purity of view no
he's the holy life lived for the sake of
Purity in terms of overcoming doubt no
how about knowledge and vision of what
is and is not the path no
is it for the sake of Purity in terms of
knowledge and vision of the way no
then is the whole life lit for the sake
of Purity in terms of knowledge and
vision no
and for the sake of what then is the
whole life lived under the blessed one
it's about knowledge and vision or
whatever the utmost goal is
which is nibana of course
virtue is not necessary
we're just newborn
just let go of things I'll start at the
end I'll have non-attachment now I don't
I'll have non-attachment now I don't
care about things anymore
which is quite uh normal so I quite a
normal View
I'll just start at the end I'll be
liking around
but you can't get to the end of you
can't reach that destination without
you know getting there walking there
traveling
so the the simile that is given
is the relay chariots
and this is the the simile that punya is
giving to saripota so that he can
understand what
so my friend I will give you an analogy
suppose that while that while king of
khosla was staying at sovereignty some
urgent business were to rise at saketa
and that between sovereignty and saketa
seven relay chariots were made ready for
him coming out of the door of the inner
coming out of the door of the inner
Palace in saviti you would get in the
first relay chariot by means of the
first relay Chariot he would reach the
second getting out of the first relay Chariot
getting out of the first relay Chariot
he would get into the second
and by means of the second and so forth
he would uh
getting out of the sixth relay Chariot
he would get into the seventh and by
means of the seventh he would finally
arrive at the door of the inner Palace
at saketa
as he arrived at his friends and
companions would ask him great king did
you come from sovereignty to the door of
the inner Palace in saketa by means of
this chariot
and he would say no and he would
describe how he got there
complete to this passion this
enchantment relinquishment cessation
freedom from suffering that's the goal
so he doesn't practice for the sake of
purifying The Virtue only
but without purifying The Virtue he
won't be able to practice for the
purification of mind
which means then he won't be able to
practice for the purification of use for
the purification of freedom from doubt
or it could be in other words unless he
starts with the first Chariot he won't
be arriving at the goal
so none of the Chariots are the goal but
without them the goal would not simply
exist and in the same sense then when the king
and in the same sense then when the king
did arrive when they asked him well did
you come by the means of this Chariot he
said no
I came by the means of Chariot after
childhood after church seven times
that's how I reached this place
I said well he abandoned the first
Chariot hmm
yeah so he doesn't need his virtue
anymore no he doesn't need to purify it
anymore it says Purity virtue so if you
like purity of virtue you need to work
on that chariot
and if you don't like it you can drop
the work I you can drop the Chariot
because virtue now it's there developed
So that's its purification of virtue
that leads to the purification of mind
you don't drop your mind either when you
finish with it but you can certainly
drop investing further effort and work
in purifying it because it has been
purified polishing the brass plate or something
polishing the brass plate or something
yeah it's clean and Polished well stop
polishing it I mean you can carry on if
you want to but and that's then the
question oh so is that the purpose to
just polish for the sake of polishing ah
no it's to move on to the next one that
needs now work on
um so is this so you have to recognize
this further to go yeah if you don't
have the idea of where you're going
yes there has to be a unifying like you
know the king wanted to get to get to
that other Town that's it
so everything else was arranged to
support that goal
so that is the whole point is to keep a
viewer essay on the reasons for practice
the intentions behind your actions keep
that in the mind because then you know
why you are keeping the virtue while
you're making the effort to be sense
restrained while you're making
um uh guarding of the sense those and so
on but if you ignore your goal uh then
it's just it can become this can become
a goal itself which means you won't be
purifying your virtue anymore
you will be assuming it you will be
holding it on the level of
oh well this practice is about
worshiping the first Chariot it's about
glorifying it it's about writing every
now and then but never leaving it to go
into the next one I never complete in
that work never committing to it
so the purification of virtue is not
something you just take on
on account of Authority or tradition or
teacher it's something you have to do
and when you do it then you won't need
an external Authority tradition or a
teacher to tell you about virtue or not
because you purified it
so that's a purification of virtue has
to lead you to the purification of the
Mind so purification of virtue that you have
so purification of virtue that you have
to do have to purify have to keep an eye
on
have to develop German versus oh he
becomes accomplished in virtue
whereby uh no unwholesome states can
cause fear in him because he knows
that his virtues accomplished he knows
he he won't break the virtue doesn't
matter what comes what challenges what
pressures him that means accomplished in
virtue that means virtue has been
purified to the to the degree necessary
to move on to the second Chariot that's
why purification of that accomplishment
of that virtue results in factual
samadhi as we said before and quoted as
other soothers like oh my word is
unbroken it's accomplished no fear no
nothing can perturb my mind on a kind of
would I do that or not because you know
what you will not do and you've been
practicing that diligently ardently and
now you recognize that no doesn't matter
you recognize that no doesn't matter
what comes these things will not be done
by Body speech and mind so purification
of The Virtue then becomes accomplished
and that's already from samadhi which is
again exactly why it would lead to then
the second step of purifying the mind
uh so purification of virtue of course
sense restraint precepts is there
anything else or is just keeping the
presets just adhere to the precepts and you're
just adhere to the precepts and you're
purifying your virtue
would that be enough
what would you need to do
abandon the Assumption of silica so
how'd you do that
um well it's understanding why
the why wholesome is wholesome and why
on the awesome is unwholesome in the
sense of in relation to the how do you
do that
well I I suppose this this idea of if
you start with purification of virtue
yeah so you don't start with you know
understanding of the Dharma and all the
other things that will kind of provide
you with answers you start with
purification of virtue can you abandon
still about the paramaster just by the
means of virtue no I think that's why
you have to have this uh final
um well actually you can but I did say
putugina can free himself without the
final goal
it's an assumption
so what is then that which a putugina
can do let alone somebody who knows the
Buddhist teaching
in regard to the keeping the precepts
that you'll actually free him from
needing the tradition needing the
authority needing a teacher
they would free him from any external
kind of criteria he would see for
himself the purification of virtue and
the accomplishment of it
what is a single Factor that's absent in
the one who doesn't see it and present
in the one who sees it
understanding their intention behind
what's the single Factor behind that
how can you understand intention sorry
seeing attending correctly well yeah but even
attending correctly well yeah but even
that it requires the same responsibility
yeah you have to take responsibility for
what you're doing including taking on
the precept it's not an external
commandment to this to any to the
slightest degree it's not
so if you need external Authority
Traditions senior agents or whatever to
keep you together from breaking precepts
you're not purifying anything
you just have enough foresight to place
yourself in the environment that will
force you to not misbehave but even that
it's only going to be a relative
so you need to be doing it yourself and
take responsibility for that
now I'm keeping the precepts because I
want to purify the virtue because I want
to purify the mind because I want to
purify the views the doubt the knowledge
and vision of what's part what it is in
part the knowledge of the path
I want to be free from suffering once
and for all
so then if ajan comes and says no no you
can do that that's not against the
vinaya that's not the criteria for you
to do it if I can say oh you mustn't do
that well that's again not a criteria
for you to not do it the criteria is the
knowledge of the precepts and then that
exactly if responsibility
for keeping the precept is taken this is
why I'm doing it you're going to feel
the kind of the the
closeness of the possibility of oh so I
could break it with no repercussions
well exactly that's why I need to start
contemplating the danger
and and and really uh consider like okay
but am I doing for why do I even want to
practice in the first place
what is my motivations what are my
reasons because according to what I want to
because according to what I want to
practice I the Buddha's instruction I
should be able to do this by myself
because it concerns only me and uh if I
need an external Authority tradition the
way how things were done or or
uh some some very like inspiring you
know non-compromising teacher to keep me
together well that is
that is not practice
sure it's if somebody has nothing and
that can make them keep the presets fine
that's better than not keeping the
precepts at all but in and of itself
that's exactly what's still about the
parama says precepts have been taken
Duty has been taken by the
responsibility for it has been covered
up
avoided dismissed
so no purification or virtue means there
will be no samadhi even if you keep the
presets for 100 years
and consequently also purifying the
virtue means there will be samadhi even
if you don't do any meditation
techniques which usually go hand in hand with not
which usually go hand in hand with not
purifying The Virtue but keeping it on
account of Authority or like a secondary
kind of okay yeah I'll do this because
it's probably good for you on some level
but really really the meat of the
practices sensation watching or nostril
observation or belly button or whatever
else I was like no first child leads you to
I was like no first child leads you to
the second one factual Somali factual
purification of the Mind
do you purify your mind through the
concentration practices and focusing and
ignoring what bothers you
well not according to the Buddha you purify
not according to the Buddha you purify
your mind by purifying your intentions
that are now revealed on account of
having traveled with the first Chariot
as far as it goes
and now on that subtle mental level the
intention of greed non-grid aversion
non-aversion distraction non-destruction
Dead starts that's apparent that's seen
that's as seen as the first you know
crude course precepts were in the
beginning so whatever you're about to do as the
so whatever you're about to do as the
Buddha instructed
with a similar mirror will you reflect
against it on having purified The Virtue
not just pontificate around it
having codified the virtue you have
intention to do this so that say this so
that think this or that well
is this leading to my harm of others is
it making the greed increase so decrease
another reason greed come or not come
same for the version
so you gotta now that traveling
of the with the second chariot
purification of the Mind entails the
purification and the clarity of the
context of what's beneficial truly and
what it's not truly beneficial
and that is determined by where the
intentions are rooted
and that is factual Somali that is
factual impatibility
no need for focusing no need for
concentration just wisdom and context no
no big surprise
and then inevitably
if you have been
purifying your intentions not acting out
of the unwholesome ones
it will lead you to the purification of
the views
so how do you purify the views then by re-establishing the
ones I'm understanding of
of what
What specifically
in other words how do you
um
how do you know you're traveling by a
third chariot
when you are abandoning metaphysical
assumptions of Southern world
true but I mean like literally how do
you know that you're in a third Chariot
if you're in a chariot
by remembering that you traveled in the
first one and then the second one so the
principle of the first one the principle
of the second one leads you to the
principle the third one
so in other words you by that by the by
the time you're in a third chariot you
will pretty much already know what's
important and why it's not important
what constitutes the successful travel
and what causes unsuccessful travel
so views
would then any views that you have any
views that might come up
would be already seen to a degree
against that which you've been doing
so and that's why as I said like if you
put aside the specific suit
the purification which you can be done
by somebody even with the wrong views if
they put the views aside
whatever views they have they don't
emphasize that they emphasize taking on
responsibility for Behavior by Body
speech intentions of the Mind
so they might have had the views still I
was in the past I was like this will it
be nibana is that this is the practice
this is not a practice but regardless of
what what thinking they've been having
but what views they've been revolving on
they did not emphasize that
they actually emphasize doing the
restraint keeping the precepts sensory
strain guiding and taking responsibility
for it and enduring the weight of that
responsibility not just sort of
misplacing it back onto the oh yeah no
no we're in this together that's why we
do this and so on so you feel you feel
lighter and account of it
so if they actually have been putting
the views aside
and practice the purification of virtue
and the purification of the mind that in
itself already constitutes the
purification of the views
so now when the views would come up
more specifically well they would
already know not to put the emphasis on
them and that's how you purify the views
and that's exactly why that leads you to
going Beyond doubt
being unable to emphasize what cannot be
emphasized being unable to pervert your
being able to doubt that which precedes
the doubt
whichever way you want to put it
so oh how do I become a social panel
what do I do what technique do I follow
what number relationship I need to
understand purify the virtue purify your intentions
purify the virtue purify your intentions
that will undo your views that will make
you go beyond doubt that's it
that's it
and then exactly
the next Chariot is oh he knows what the
practice is and what the practice isn't
he knows exactly what it would lead to
Nirvana and what wouldn't he knows for
himself he sees it
okay the next Chariot if he follows that
which leads to nibana well he knows what
nibana is now it's right there
the knowledge and vision
and this is important because
the views come first
in everyone's experience
so you can't change that people would
hope okay putting the views aside means
these views will stop coming up for me
no they won't
but you can use your discernment to not
allow yourself to emphasize them and act
out of them
she's like well yeah I think it's like
this but I think it's like that I think
it might be like this but
am I pretty find The Virtue am I keeping
the precepts guiding all the sensors
have I taken responsibility am I feeling
the weight
of of of my investment so to speak
in this practice
or do I feel absolved because I found a
greater bigger thing in this community
is this religion it's this practices
this Meditation Center is this technique
is this whatever
um
so the danger isn't
in there being these views the danger is
sort of becoming Intoxicated by them
exactly or basically the danger is uh
allowing yourself to shift back the
emphasis onto the views and kind of oh
yes yes you know when I appreciate sure
you know but really
uh drift away from from the from the
from the quiet emphasis yeah from the
emphasis on that and that is you you
know you hear that like you would see
that you know people are like yeah yeah
eight precepts and stuff but that's it
so they kind of brushed aside this is
the factual thing obvious to everyone
keeping the precepts virtue
now listen this is the practice and it's
just going to be now for information
about the views that's it when you hear
people describe the practice it's just
people describing views and opinions
as to as this was this was it which
provides information satisfying answer
or not not satisfying answer but that's
it
she's like yeah okay but how do I purify
this virtue then that then leads me to
the purification of the Mind
how they purify these views I mean I can
take it or leave it sure but what do I
do well you know Consciousness never
changes it's always there you just need
to see it be here now
okay but how do I do that
well by seeing that Consciousness is
unchanging by being here well you're
just saying the same thing in different
words how do I do it what do I do where
are these chariots that I need to travel
with same when it comes to even if
people quote that the suit does oh yes
okay so how to do it here by seeing not
self but how do I do that so by seeing
that you can't own things
again you're just giving the synonyms of
the same thing how do I do it
because the Buddha didn't just come out
of a blue and just said listen there's
no self you're done
the whole gradual training
okay so precept so so what do you just
keep the presets yeah what is the next
step now will the next step be on the
level of well this is how you purify the
precepts further
this is how you'll then see a dentist in
your mind or just like oh well yeah you
keep the precepts now relax watch your
nostrils get your kamatan focus on the
objects concentrate and concentrate and
concentrate and everything else we'll
just nibana or Jana
a diligent monk does he sit watching his
nostrils feeling Blissful no he purifies
his mind and I can't developing four
foundations of mindfulness and then he
feels Blissful because he's deathless
because he's free from prison he's
suffering cannot touch him I mean as I
said when we started this even that
whole like he recollects his unbroken
virtue for which he taken responsibility
and he knows now because he'd take a
responsibility that he cannot break it
he'll never know that if he hasn't taken
responsibility because well I'm not
breaking it here because these urgents
you know will kick me out and so on
oh but what if my circumstance change
do I know for sure then when there is
nobody to punish me or tell me off or
fear of blame or something like that in
this this environment if there is no
such thing there
do I know for sure I will still not do
this
or if the circumstances change slightly
oh I don't know
oh what what purification have you done
none it's like a prison guy in prison
as I said circumstantially it's better
than allowing it to be done but we're
not talking about that that's that's how
Layman should live his life not the one
who wants to practice
so the point is then oh if you've taken
the responsibility the time if you have
invested every time will come and he
knows no matter the circumstances that are not
no matter the circumstances that are not
in my control what comes my way what
Temptation what pressure what kind of
things discomforts discontentment
accomplish the virtue means knowing that
he will not do anything against their
virtue and that gives rise to Pleasant
abiding even up
the samadhi but it's also
this responsibility I think initially
I mean painful so so people of course
people who will well there is a reason
that that people would willingly go into
into a factor of silhouma so willingly
put it on there because it actually
at this kind of immediate level it makes
him more pleasant for me or makes it
less unpleasant
so in the long run
yeah that's why I will give so much
Faith too yeah it's external yeah
um form or this Tech meditation
technique and now that you mention Faith
that's another equally misunderstood
thing our faith means I'll just be brain
dead devoted to the instruction of this
person as in inspiration behind it did I
get behind this instruction no faith
means put your views second keep the
virtue guard the sensitors first because
you won't see a direct reason for to do
it your views are telling you otherwise
the whole world is telling you otherwise
but you have enough faith in what you
understood from what the Buddha
instructed so out of that Faith you don't revolve
so out of that Faith you don't revolve
around oh what is this and is that
what is the etymology of this word no
you put all that aside
and you actually take responsibility for
The Virtue and you guard the sense those
and you pretty much maintain and develop
and and and increase the wholesome
context behind your intentions
out of faith
you have no other reason other than
Faith no I'll do this because it makes
sense to that extent and I have faith
that the Buddha was right let me just
start doing this while the views and all
the answers I seek and all the doubts
and insecurities I'll just put that
second until I deal with these things
first that is the faith that and you
could see how that Faith could equally
result in
because you're actually doing the work
so it's very faith that faith is very
different to like inspiration exactly
exactly what I wanted to say as well as
that's about taking responsibility for
virtue it very much also pertains to
it very much also pertains to
being able even to purify the views by
putting views aside because you have to
also because views aren't usually something
because views aren't usually something
that you take responsibility for
consciously even hold I I I think this
and I think that they're more just very
fundamental like assumptions about
things that you take so much for granted
that you don't even take responsibility
or realize that no this is a view that I
have so it means I could it might not be
right or it could I could not do this so
but so that's more subtle even than the
responsibility for
actions and and uh and things so that's
why you kind of need to start with that
which then
sort of shows you that oh even these
views that I hold I am responsible for
holding them so Ben let me
I I don't
let me put them aside as you said and
continue to do this which I see is
beneficial
by putting the views aside
can purifying virtue and purify your
mind he does actually start to create a
reference point for those views which is
a new view sure but it's the right view
it's the view that has arisen as a
result of practice that has not been
acting out of and emphasizing the views
you can see them as views in a sense
yeah you're just blind to them being
viewed exactly yeah but that whole thing
of like you cannot have the views that's
for sure you can't just drop them you
can just choose to not hold them but
what you can do is choose to not
prioritize them anymore
are the faith purify your virtue purify
your mind and that will then
diminish these views which which gives
right to what the right gives rise to
what the right view is so in other words
you would replace your wrong views with
the Right View
view that knows what the path is and
what the path isn't it's like um you
also you can't not have faith you have
to have faith in something whether it's
drugs or or Escape or you know whatever
you're finding your safety whatever
you're investing effort in maintaining
your sense of safety that is where you
have your faith in whatever that is
whether it's sensuality tradition
Authority family possessions inevitable
yeah exactly in as much as the views are
inevitable a degree of faith and belief
is inevitable but what is not inevitable
is to lose your reason in regard to it
and not be aware of your situation
within it
so and that will lead to Faith whereby
that Faith becomes wisdom yeah Faith
basically informed informed faith not
faith on a kind of emotional experience
and feeling that I have when I listen to
this or read that and I say wait what is
factually good for me well
good for me well
to find a doctor who gives me an
instruction recipe
recipe
so how will I know that's correct How
will I know that will cure me well
by initially taking it on faith and
beginning the application of it heading
to a diet
protecting of the wound not increasing
the infection and so on out of faith
and then as you as your health improves
on the continent you won't have that
Faith anymore because you saw for
yourself dedicure
but the faith
doesn't lead to the end of faith
is is oh executing yeah it's the wrong
view yeah it's like yeah it's a it's
basically a faith for which you haven't
taken responsibility so I will continue
to believe it because it's because it
makes me feel better it makes me feel
well makes me feel absolved from
responsibility and it's incredibly
dangerous because of that because of
that so intoxication you willingly
forsake your reason and discernment you
don't you don't realize okay it's
because it's pleasurable and that
happens to people especially like when
it comes to you know following the
instructions of others in the religion
on account of being Toxic
self-intoxicated by your own faith and
avoiding responsibility
you neglected the obvious things they
were wrong right in front of you you
ignored you turned a blind eye and then
later on show when things went too far
then it's like oh wow yeah I don't know
how that happened it's like this
charismatic leader he looks like he's or
she looks like they've got it sorted so
I'll just you know yeah I'll just submit
that nothing for myself yeah
and even if that charismatically there
is the Buddha himself
and when people did just follow him
because he was so charismatic and
inspiring he dismissed and told him off
told him to get lost to stop following
him because they're not practicing what
he's saying and then those people they
didn't follow him but actually fulfill
the teaching like in the suitors were
not a hunt when a person becomes an
out-handed Freedom mind it's always
um sort of portrayed with a description
of ah the teacher has been worshiped so
they truly yeah that's the only way to
pay this back to the Buddha is to
fulfill his teachings
so we I paid my respects now I don't owe
anything to anyone including the Buddha
himself but yeah that's much you know more
but yeah that's much you know more
insecure more full of that
requiring more of diligence discomfort
endurance than just no no this is the
greatest teaching I'm a believer I'm
safe say you what you mentioned now you have
say you what you mentioned now you have
have doubt coming up and you have these
views coming up so
in in in light of
this discussion and this sutah how do
you deal with it how do you deal with
the doubt and the mind and the
insecurity and anxiety and everything
else views regarding around that and
lack of answers what do you do in terms
of
what we just described
well yeah like in terms of what you just
described if you have been taking on the
The Virtue and say you did so you did
for example you're doing The Virtue yeah
you're keeping it you're practicing your
sense restraint you're secluded you're
moderating you're eating
becoming aware of your intentions more
obviously and now you're just racked
with doubt and pain and discomfort on a
mental level what do you do then
see the doubt as doubt
how do we do that so doubt will be
I wouldn't really be just another view
that I had to do an accountant review
um potentially but if you're enjoying it
on the right level so that's that's what
you do first you endure it on the right
level what does that mean it means not turning
what does that mean it means not turning
we're back onto the second Chariot what
does that mean in terms of the second
chariot
um including on the right level what
does that mean in terms of purification
of the mind or cheat Elemental Universe
purification of the Mind
so pre-division delusion non-create
non-version non-delusion what does that
mean in those terms
and during an on the right level not
acting out of it what of the doubt of
the unpleasant the displeasure of the so not
unpleasant the displeasure of the so not
acting out of greed or aversion or
distraction in regard to discomfort of
the doubt
and you will be able to see that and not
act out of it if you have been keeping
the virtue and practicing sense and
strength yeah otherwise so that's what
you do basically you don't engage with
it on the level of the views because
obviously doubt will just feed more
doubt if you act out of it which is not
sealer which is not exactly it's not
along those principles so of course you
might you'll get but then wait but what
do you do what you are I do what I have
been doing where is this intention
rooted in in this particular instance of
this doubt or this anxiety oh I want to
get rid of it
how does the monk free himself from
hindrances so from from mind kind of
obsessed with sensuality or real will or
doubt not be doing this or that but by
seeing through with yonisomanasikara so
that which hinders you in terms of the
central desire you see through it and
recognize that oh there's a beautiful
object and pleasure in regard to it that
I'm acting out of or in this case or I
must get rid of it oh so there is this
beautiful object that besets me an
aversion towards it that I'm acting out
of it so by seeing through with that
proper attention he re-establishes the
context and that's what the Buddha was
describing as well like in we mentioned
a number of times lately that the whole
the two types of thought that he decided
to think wholesome not on wholesome and
then when unwholesome comes up so when
hindrances come up
oh I'll just I'll just I'll just focused
on a part of my body until I forget
about this
no you won't find that in the suit is
for sure
but he did say he he he was doing was ah
so when there is the thought of
sensuality or cruelty or real will and
you could even say if doubt or anxiety
is like he that was there but he did not
attend to it wrongly at the face value
with the attitude I must get rid of this
I must say it out of this aversion
towards this instead no I would just
keep investing my effort in on the level
of the context so this thought of
sensuality that's here
has it been kind of leading to uh my
harm or my benefit in the past how about
in the present is it for my good or not
or is it for benefit of others is it
helpful is it pressuring is it
increasing with the weakness or the
strength is it increasing of dispassion
or passion
just by pondering on those things in
face of the sensual desire Central
desire will subside because that is
really what it is that is the real
context of the centrality
ill will cruelty doubt yes sure it would
be important to know this but I'm
obviously now emotionally gripped by
doubt and I want to get rid of the pain
of it which means any answers I'm
seeking on account of doubting mind will
be secondary all I'm doing is fueling
the aversion towards pain and that's a
hindrance in itself
so what do I do well I attend I tend to
it rightly or I see through it pretty
much so there is this doubt that the
face value is trying to make me act I
don't act I Endure it and I see what's
through it oh aversion to pain is the
goal of this seemingly seeking for an
answer that my mind is trying to
overwhelm me with whenever I was a verse
and active out of pain how did that
result did that bring pain to increase or
did that bring pain to increase or
decrease did that overcome doubt once
and for all or not did it lead to my
harm how about does it lead to composure
or distract oh look doubt is gone
because I basically I undone the
attitude that was underlying uh hidden
behind this this doubt that I was trying
to get rid of but asking those questions
that you've asked would be impossible if
you're acting out of it if you're being
absorbed in the content somebody again
somebody might hear this now and they
have experience of doubt and then they
say I'm not an act out of that I must do
what decision said and they start asking
these questions rooted in trying to get
rid of Doubt well they will not be able
to see through that and abandon that
unless they have already been purifying
their mind on account of taking
responsibility and purifying their
virtue that's why it doesn't work that's
why it stays on the level of abstraction
and Views even if it isn't so
but those people who have taken
responsibility for The Virtue purify
their virtue accomplish themselves in it
purify the intentions behind their
actions purify their mind develop
somebody on account of it they will
catch this pretty much soon
if not immediately
oh wait okay yeah I shouldn't be getting
without but now I'm telling myself that
I should be getting you know to get rid
of the doubt thus I will not act out of
that intention
so I'll let doubt be there and I'll keep
seeing through it
and by seeing through it the Mind
becomes unhindered from that which
hinders you
but it hinders you not because of itself
in the in and of itself it hinders you
because you had no perspective in regard
to it
as well the right type of Faith because
for example when you have
when there is doubt
or even any of the hindrances actually
in order to not act out of that doubt
because like your whole mind and
everything that you've been doing for
years and years in your only way of
finding some solution to it or finding
this oh this will give me confidence
this will give me Faith this will give
me more you know what I need in order to
keep going
that you know I need to find the answer
to this or I need to seek a reassurance
or something
and you need to not do that like you need to
you need to not do that like you need to
at some point not seek safety in the
things that you've been used to seeking
safety and why there's no
why
because it doesn't lead to safety
exactly because it's rooted in already
being unsafe and it and it and it
actually only what you've what you are
you know the more you're asking for
something to give you Faith the more you
are actually diminishing your
possibility of having any faith because
that's that's the point like the more of
like uh the more in in a direction of
non-responsibility you're traveling yeah
you're avoiding it and avoiding it
you're like cultivating doubt not
cultivating exactly but that's very and
and that and that's why faith is
absolutely necessary because there is
nothing else no no external no you know
nobody else or nothing else can you know
do it for you there's no confirmation
except your own well I think it pretty
much would come down today wouldn't it
even this like you know like we talk
about enduring things
even people look many people you know
obviously people understand that but
number of people would not even
understand that
because you value the citizens like well
no it's about you know dealing and doing
stuff it's like well yeah but how you go
about it matters
um when you say
you need to endure things without acting
out of it
basically yeah you need a degree of
Faith to not talk immediately
just just to that extent and then you
see okay this is what I do I don't reply
to but with thoughts of ugly and ugly
and ugly and concentrate in nostrils no
I see through it
I see that this is just a beautiful
object inducible of lust for which I am
responsible when you re-establish the
context the beautiful object remains
standing there in the world as they
would have said but there is no exactly
but if you haven't had that initial
Faith to endure and not take tired of
this Duty and now this is what I must do
in a dress which is all rooted in a
version towards that which making you
feel uncomfortable
so without that Faith you just won't be
able to to restrain you won't be able to
not act and then even if you're doing
the enduring you're doing it so if you
have faith though and not take it out
and stay in that seemingly overwhelming
position but I'm not dealing with this
but it needs to be dealt with I need to
endure it out of faith well then the
path can become apparent that's what it
said even in the sutras I think so in a
gutra did like a a noble disciple so one
with the Right View maybe even
sakuragami has not become an anagami yet
because he lacks faith
to a degree obviously he doesn't like
faith in the Buddha and the teaching so
oh but where does he well he lacks Faith
just to that kind of initial degree to
not act out of central thoughts or
thoughts of ill will to that extent he's
not freeing himself from Central
thoughts and thoughts of ill because he
acts out of them
even if not necessarily acting towards
sensuality he acts out of it he
distracts himself he dismisses it he
contemplates a Suba to get rid of the
pain behind the pressure of sensuality
not to just see the nature sensuality
that's what I keep saying like it's
actually better if you practice a Suba
or loving kindness
before you you your mind is great with
lost or your will not in response to it
and when I say practice before I don't
mean as a Mindless technique and motion
you go through I mean no re invoke the
image of beautiful that would otherwise
induce lust and start seeing that within
that start seeing the ugly the Peril is
the dangers the hidden trap and debate
so the context needs to be developed
sufficiently enough so that it doesn't
move when these thoughts are present and
the context moves when you act out of it
and you act out of it when you don't
have enough Faith to endure the thoughts
that are present without acting out of
it
So to that extent the noble disciple if
he lacks the faith that would enable him
to not immediately
resolve the central desire or get rid of
their will thoughts he won't be free
from those things because he's
perpetuating them through his ignorant
action so it should be obvious to anybody
so it should be obvious to anybody
listening to this right talks when we
talk about endurance it's not on the
same level as bearing of the elements
you know like they're the suit as they
said it's translated as endurance but
it's it's not the same word I'm talking
about like also endurance means I just bear
like also endurance means I just bear
things mindlessly like that suta says
well you bear heat cold thirst words of
others mindlessly sure when we talk
about endurance you realize oh it's a
completely different level it's the it's
the endurance that pertains to
abandoning all of the things in that
sutar first not acting out
having faith and the gradual training
so the whole point of that would then be
like okay
the problem is in me being affected but
if I act out of directly towards these
things that affect me I'm perpetuating
the fact that I'm being affected
so Faith as a factor then it's not just
existing in somebody before he becomes a
sottabana and then he faith is a
spiritual power as the Buddha called it
which means later on you use the same
faith do not act out of things immediately to
do not act out of things immediately to
not get rid of them immediately so that
you can endure them because you already
know you have confidence that enduring
them on this level will lead to seeing
through them
and that's when you cease to be hindered
by any of the things that are otherwise
hindrances that does not mean that those things
that does not mean that those things
cease to arise just means you're
incapable of not seeing through them
when they arise saying them as
hindrances see well no they're not
hindrances anymore that's the point
seeing them as what used to hinder you
when you attended to it wrongly that's
what he says if he does not attend
rightly to the sign of the beautiful
Central hindrance if he attends rightly
to the sign of the beautiful no
sensuality hindrance and same goes for
all the other hindrances
so enduring things rightly would then
result in purification of the views that
will make you go beyond doubt
and that's done on account of the second
childhood as you said not acting out of
intentions rooted in aversion sensuality
ill will
greed all sorts of kind of layers of the
same three principles distraction as
well like distraction is also like quite
often ends up being justified means of
dealing with things
our focus on Sensations
some distracted from the pressing image
that bothers me and emotionally disturbs
me
I'll go in a state of you know neither
here nor there half asleep
because that's peaceful not thinking
about what I'm subjected to is peaceful
and people then conflate the successful
meditation practice with successful
degree of ignoring the problem
this endurance that we're talking about
I think is also integral to
in mindfulness in the sense that
um
like mindfulness of the body mindfulness
of feeling
they they
these are discerned as a relationship to
what is presently enduring in terms of
if you exactly if you don't yeah if you
think of mindfulness of the body in
terms of observation turning that into
an object like my body is an object yeah
right that that is not seeing the
relationship between
or whatever is you know occupying you
know whatever is in front of me being
determined by my Beating Heart or how do
I feel how do I feel
while I'm seeing this yeah how do I feel
while I'm getting those words yeah how
do I feel while I'm bearing heat and
cold am I enduring the feeling on a kind
of bearing the elements and it's the
relationship exactly the feeling yeah
and the bones you won't find the feeling
in your senses where you're observing
things so unless you need to look at
that background peripheral in regard to
what's there in front of you
there is no mindfulness for you in
regards to not being when you said not
being able to act in certain ways
does that mean basically understanding
horse and as wholesome or harmful as
harmful and beneficial is beneficial
because why would one be unable to act
because you haven't been acting long
enough and you took responsibility for
avoiding that act
out of faith
and then out of seeing benefit directly
for yourself yes but then you're
starting basically to see well yeah of
course you know the other six chariots
don't don't come after the first one
they're already waiting there so you see
what's in front of you if you travel
through this so you are already seeing
the purification of your intentions on
account of purifying your virtue you are
seeing the purification of views later
on if you keep purifying your virtue
um so it's a it's a good it's again it's
a good criteria to go by ask yourself
if say there is no Authority there is no
immediate like
um
tradition family even the law
would I
still uphold the value
uphold the value
of sense restraint
guarding of the sensors not acting out
and not breaking the presets because I
choose to do it and I've been choosing
to do it for so long
but there is no
other thing to prevent it from doing
well there is fear of jail
being beaten up retribution being kicked
out of what you deem to be yours which
you take part all these things prevent
you from doing it losing your Lifeboat
is wrong yeah yes they're all factual
reasons but none of those all of those
reasons at the same time yeah it's good
they didn't force you to be virtues but
at the same time they also take away
responsibility for that virtue that's
why virtue and duty silabata paramasa is
a factual Factor
so you need it but you don't need it as
a Fetter and that's the difference I'm
describing yeah if you don't take responsibility it
yeah if you don't take responsibility it
will be a fatter and if you feel fully
Justified because virtue is always good
well you'll feel fully justified in just
worshiping the first Chariot and not
even sitting in it let alone reaching
the second one
and that is exactly why people who are
not free from Silverado paramasa would
not see
the purification of the mind for what it
is
which is purification of intentions a
reason at the time
not a blanket technique concentration or
approach that you can just have
regardless of what state the mind is in
yes so are you independent of the
concrete circumstances you find yourself
in the more you can say yes to that the
more you are moving towards the noble
ones who are actually factually
independent not on your circumstances
exactly exactly and the more your mind
will be composed and gladdened and
joyful and account of The Unbroken
virtue that you I'm accomplished in so
whether I'm in the forest or in the city
things that I will not do
remain clear and kind of immovable the
context of that remains immovable
and that is something you trained for
it's not something that is as again
people would kind of naively hope you
take on true tradition through an
authority to us some sort of technique or practice
to us some sort of technique or practice
or whatever have a special experience
and now you become unable to break your
virtue you become unable to break your
virtue if you have cultivate
non-breaking of it responsibly for
sufficient period of time
and then you start recognizing the
factual somebody that comes the factual
safety that comes as a result of it not
oh I was virtuous so Davis will protect
me well they might
but that's not something you see for
yourself no can you see for yourself but
you can see for yourself as a factual
protection is
mind unmoved
mind cannot
act and resist out of aversion as much
as it be cannot turn against itself as I
was saying before cannot turn around and
bite me if it's upset with the world
cannot give me sleepless nights can you
give me suicidal depressive thoughts
because it's been tamed and it's been
Tamed by me who's been avoiding acting
in certain directions and then guarding
of the sensors and and sustaining of the
right context in regard to it I have
been making the work uh putting the work
in there diligently as a result of it
the mind is calm and you see it and you
have a direct verification of why this
is worth doing
so not acting out yeah because that's
always the comes down to that the
problem of it pressure to act out and
then acting up yeah I know what I meant
is that like you can't
Escape responsibility basically you can
not act in certain ways because you
don't want to go to jail or don't want
to be kicked out or anything but you
don't see anything more immediate
can make any difference it's you can
always choose
in in what in regard to whatever you
choose it's you who chooses
theoretically it's yes if you speak
about Theory from the point of view of
the third Chariot yes but that's not
seen one thing is to say that another
thing is are you saying that an account
of being already accomplished in a
virtue when it will be factually true
now it's not factually true it's
theoretically true and it's good to
strive for that but it's not an answer
and it's not an explanation but it is an
explanation but it's not an answer
so yes
you will be in the third Chariot if you
travel with the first two and you cannot
not be in the third Chariot sure but are
you so that's my point
so that's my point
you are always doing it you it's always
on you but that's not seen and that's
not how it's practically lived
okay now I gotta do this regardless of
the environment and the tradition and
the requirements and the expectations
and then if you do it like that then you
will then see the benefit for yourself
there and then also miss wholesome and
wholesome is unwholesome regardless of
the environment regardless of the
tradition and that's what it said the one the
and that's what it said the one the
sodapana who is free himself from
syllable paramasa gone beyond that he
like even if the whole world says oh the
Buddha's destruction was wrong he'll
know that the world is wrong
not because he's so blinded by the faith
in the Buddha because his direct
verification amid suffering amidst Brink basically of
amid suffering amidst Brink basically of
existence depression overwhelming pain
he cannot suffer
because of the purification he developed
and the way he sees things now not
because of he got rid of all of this and
nothing ever comes to bother him
so the confidence cannot be shaken
because I mean this is it like when a
midst of the life-threatening pain and
fear and anxiety the Mind does not turn
against you or itself
you don't suffer
there is nothing greater that can verify
your success
in terms of practice so suffering and
freedom from it that's all the Buddha
teaches and that's all he needs to teach
and that's all you need to know really
because that's what it all boils down to